Guide to the Bureau of Police, Department of Public Safety, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1896-1936 AIS.1972.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bureau of Police, Department of Public Safety, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records
1896-1936
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh (Pa.). Bureau of Police
AIS.1972.11
12 microfilm_reels (1 oversize box and 12 vols.)
Contain general orders, arrest dockets, complaint reports, reports of investigations and arrests, prisoner receipt books, duty roster, correspondence and criminal photo album for the #4 (Oakland) and #10 (Hazelwood) district police stations. Digital reproductions of portions of the collection are available online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
Contain general orders, arrest dockets, complaint reports, reports of investigations and arrests, prisoner receipt books, duty roster, correspondence and criminal photo album for the #4 (Oakland) and #10 (Hazelwood) district police stations.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the Criminal Photograph Album are available online.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mike Coon, Jack Simpson, and Art Harger, September 11, 1972.
Custodial History
These records were discovered abandoned in the loft of the King's Court, 3807 Forbes Avenue, which at one time was the headquarters of the No. 4 (Oakland) police station. Mike Coon, Jack Simpson, and Art Harger, owners of a copying service on the third floor of King's Court and renters of the loft, gave these records to the Archives Service Center.
Previous Citation
Bureau of Police, Department of Public Safety, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1896-1936, AIS.1972.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Homewood (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Police stations -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Criminals -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Crime -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Police reports -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Police -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Government; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Hazelwood (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Oakland (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.). Department of Public Safety; Pittsburgh (Pa.). Bureau of Police
- Headquarters, I.
  - General Orders, 1923-1924, 1930-1932 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 1)
    Scope and Content Notes
    Contains memoranda and communications from the Superintendent of Police to the District Police Commissioners. Subjects include: complaints of laxity of law enforcement, civilian intercessions on behalf of reassigned officers, transfers, promotions, lists of furloughed officers in pursuance of city ordinance decreasing number of policemen (Dec. 31, 1931), traffic violations, list of trial board cases, monthly statements or the Police and Detective Protective Association, depression relief fund (donations, disbursements, pledges).
    General order #135, dated October 23, 1923, concerns plans for the visit of Lloyd George to the city. General order #95 dated, January 12, 1924, notes a complaint by the mayor, Hon. Wm. A. Magee, that he has been informed that there have been a number of violations of the law and that the police have been lax in the performance of their duties.
    General order #3 A 31, dated Jan. 15, 1931, notifies the inspectors that the United States Government is anxious to secure an accurate census of the unemployed in the city of Pgh. and asks that instructions be issued to all police officers that they assist the enumeration in every way possible.
  - Criminal Photograph Album, ca. 1919-1920 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    Contains photographs of suspect, name of suspect, residence of suspect, crime, occupation, date of arrest, age, height, weight, and physical description.
  - Patrolman Assessment Book, 1921-1923 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    For each officer records permissions for bonds, special gifts, and police association dates.
  - Record of Recovery of Lost and Stolen Goods, Apr. 7, 1913-Jan. 4, 1932 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    Each entry contains: date, articles recovered, value of articles, from whom recovered, officer, by whom claimed, to whom delivered.
  - Wanted Poster, 1924 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    $50 reward offered for arrest and delivery of Wesley G. Burrow convicted of desertion; he had escaped from the U.S. Disciplinary Barracks, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas.
- #4 Station, Oakland, II.
  - Correspondence, 1.
    Subjects include: instructions to officers on handling prisoners (searching, papers to be taken, prisoners to be separated if arrested and suspected of a grave offense); instructions on behavior of officers when giving testimony at hearings; instructions on arrest and docketing procedures, report or inspection of police station (1922; station found to be unsanitary, dirty and verminous); patrolman and detail assignments; traffic problems and instructions on arrest or summoning of traffic violation; raiding of hotels and business houses; violations of Sunday sales and labor prohibitions; wage scale for Pgh. policemen; citizens complaints; notices by individuals of absence from city and request for property watch.
    File for 1921 contains a list of draft dodgers with note that there is a $50 award for each apprehension. In a letter of Oct. 31. 1921, John C. Calhoun, Police Commissioner, exhorts the officers of #4 station to get out the vote in the general election of Nov. 8, 1921. He admonished them to "See that those you get out [,] vote the republican ticket." He continues, "If we don't try to help those that help us [,] we are ingrates and should not have the positions we now hold, but should get out of the cities [sic] employ and hunt a new position."
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Volume 1, 1921-1923, 1926, 1931, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
  - [Arrest Docket] Commissioners Docket, Police Inspection Docket, 1893-1933; 2.
    Each entry contains: arrest no., name of prisoner, address, age, color, nationality, occupation, marital status, literacy, day and hour arrested, place arrested, arresting officer, charge, forfeit, magistrate, disposition, articles found on prisoner, signature. Monthly and annual recapitulation contains: no. of males and females, ages, nationalities, marital status, color, occupation, charges, dispositions. Arranged chronologically with monthly and annual recapitulation.
    - Volume 1, Feb. 3, 1893-March 29, 1896 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    - Volume 2, Feb. 1, 1903-Aug. 1, 1905 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 2)
    - Volume 3, Aug. 1, 1907-Apr. 30, 1909 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 3)
    - Volume 4, May 1, 1909-Aug. 31, 1912 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 3)
    - Volume 5, June 1, 1915-Oct. 22, 1918 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 3)
    - Volume 6, Oct. 23, 1918-Oct. 5, 1919; October ?, 1919-November 15, 1920; Feb. 5-6, 1925 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 4)
    - Volume 7, Nov. 12, 1930-May 15, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 4)
  - Record of Arrests, 1920-1923; 3.
    - Volume 1, Aug. 1, 1920-Mar. 6, 1921 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 4)
    - Volume 2, April 8, 1922-July 7, 1922; April 3, 1923-April 5, 1923 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 4)
  - Reports or Investigations and Arrests, 4.
    Details given include nature and character of crime (accident, suicide, robbery, suspicious person, drunkenness, visiting disorderly house), time of crime, location, names, evidence.
    - Volume 1, 1924-1932, 1933, 1935 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 5)
  - Complaint Reports, 5.
    Gives crime classification, name and address of complainant, date or occurrence of crime, place of occurrence of crime, date and time crime reported by complainant, officer assigned to investigate complaint, details or complaint.
    - Volume 1, 1935 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 5)
  - Robbery Reports, 1934-1935; 6.
    Each entry gives: Serial No., time of report, method of report, name and address of complainant, occurrence time and place, patrolman on post at time or complaint, details of complaint, disposition, time transmitted by telephone.
    - Volume 1, Sept. 1, 1934-Dec. 31, 1935 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 6)
  - [Journal] Complaint Book, 1922-1923; 7.
    Daily log which contains complaints, reports, instructions to patrolmen and other miscellaneous information. Some volumes contain lists or stolen and recovered automobiles.
    - Volume 1, Sept. 22, 1923-Mar. 3, 1924; Apr. 29, 1924-Dec. 1, 1924 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 6)
    - Volume 2, Nov. 3, 1927-June 20, 1928 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 6)
    - Volume 3, July 1, 1928-March 27, 1929 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 6)
    - Volume 4, Mar. 27, 1929-Nov. 28, 1929 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 7)
    - Volume 5, Nov. 20, 1929-Aug. 11, 1930 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 7)
    - Volume 6, Jan. 1, 1930-Oct. 15, 1931 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 7)
    - Volume 7, Jan. 27, 1933-July 16, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 7)
    - Volume 8, July 17, 1933-Nov. 25, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 8)
    - Index, 1920-1923 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 8)
  - Duty Roster, 1926-1933; 8.
    - Volume 1, May 22, 1926-Feb. 28, 1927 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 8)
    - Volume 2, Mar. 1, 1927-Dec. 21, 1927 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 8)
    - Volume 3, Aug. 4, 1929-May 25, 1930 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 8)
    - Volume 4, Mar. 19, 1931-Dec. 31, 1931 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 9)
    - Volume 5, Jan. 1, 1932-Oct. 20, 1932 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 9)
    - Volume 6, Oct. 20, 1932-July 31, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 9)
  - [Patrolman] Time Roll, 1917, 1927-1931; 9.
    Each entry gives: name of patrolman, rank, days, rate per day, amount due, remarks.
    - Volume 1, 1917; May 1927-Jan. 1931 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 9)
- #6 Station, Homewood, III.
  - Photograph of Members of Homewood Auxiliary Police, Div. 5, ca. 1930 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 10)
- #10 Station, Hazelwood, IV.
  - Record of Arrests, 1919-1920; 1.
    - Volume 1, Oct. 8, 1919-Oct. 16, 1920 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 10)
  - Complaint Reports, 2.
    Gives crime classification, name and address of complainant, date of occurrence of crime, place of occurrence of crime, date and time crime reported by complainant, officer assigned to investigate complaint, details of complaint.
    - Volume 1, 1929-1931 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 10)
  - [Journal] Complaint Book, 1922, 1928-1933; 3.
    - Volume 1, May 1, 1922-Dec. 31, 1922 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 11)
    - Volume 2, Aug. 13, 1928-July 21, 1929 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 11)
    - Volume 3, Oct. 15, 1931-July 17, 1932 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 11)
    - Volume 4, July 18, 1932-Jan. 4, 1933 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 11)
  - Receipt Book for Recovered Automobiles, 1928-1929; 4.
    Contains miscellaneous prisoners receipts, 1935-1936.
    - Volume 1, Aug. 13, 1928-1929 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 12)
  - Prisoners Receipt Book for Property and Forfeits, 1932-1936; 5.
    - Volume 1, July 19, 1932-Mar. 28, 1935; Apr. 1935-Feb. 1936 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 12)
  - [Patrolmen] Time Roll, 1909-1913, 1925-1932; 6.
    Each entry gives: name of patrolman, rank, days, rate per day, amount due, and remarks.
    - Volume 1, 1909-1913 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 12)
    - Volume 2, March 1925-June 1932 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 12)
  - [Arrest Docket] Commissioners Docket, Police Inspection Docket, 1909-1916; 7.
    Each entry contains: arrest no., name of prisoner, address, age, color, nationality, occupation, marital status, literacy, day and hour arrested, place arrested, arresting officer, charge, forfeit, magistrate, disposition, articles found on prisoner, signature. Arranged chronologically with monthly and annual recapitulation.
    - Volume 1, Aug, 1, 1914-Dec. 31, 1916; Oct. 26-31, 192? (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 12)
    - Volume 2, Feb. 2, 1909-Apr. 30, 1912 (Microfilm-cabinet 1, Drawer 6, Reel 12)